Arvind Chandra

Work Permit: U.S. Citizen → Los Angeles, CA. → (614) 477-8901 arvchandra@gmail.com → linkedin.com/in/arvchandra

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with 15 years experience in full-stack web application development, with recent project experience in Python/Django (8 years) and React (4 years). Experienced in leading technical teams, architecting applications, aligning business needs with optimized technical solutions, and providing excellent customer support and incident resolution. Proven success across industries, including digital media, startups, and government consulting.

SKILLS

Languages: Python, Typescript, Javascript, jQuery, SQL, HTML, CSS, SCSS

Frameworks: Django, React, REST API, Postgres, MySQL, Git, Docker, Cypress, AWS (EC2, S3, Lambda)

Processes: CI/CD (GitHub Actions), Agile/Scrum Development, Database Administration, Test Automation, ETL

EXPERIENCE

Career/Personal Development (Sabbatical)

June 2024 - Current

- Completed advanced coursework on Udemy.com to strengthen skills in Django, Python, and React.
- Designed and developed a full-stack Django/React application integrating Al-driven prompts and third-party APIs.
- Pursued freelance projects in music production and video editing, expanding creative and technical versatility.
- Traveled to India to take care of my parents and oversee the construction of our new house.

Hone December 2021 - June 2024

Senior Software Engineer

Los Angeles, CA - Remote

- Developed the Django/Python/React/Typescript/Postgres Learning Management Platform and the Django Admin.
- Led the redesign of the Surveys application by writing technical design documents in Confluence, managing JIRA
 projects, and designing/implementing the Postgres database schema, Django data models and REST Framework API,
 React/Typescript components, and automated testing framework (Python unittest and Cypress frontend tests).
- Led a technical debt resolution strategy in collaboration with the CTO, which resulted in consistent allotment of time and resources to fixing bugs and improving user experience.
- Retained our highest-revenue customer (worth \$200,000/year) by resolving critical data integrity issues, which involved writing Django management commands and raw SQL to quickly discover and fix erroneous data mappings.
- Deployed the Docker application to AWS through a customized GitHub Actions pipeline, which included linting, unit and integration testing, and feature-flag testing on both Staging and Production servers.

Industry Dive March 2020 - July 2021

Senior Software Engineer

Washington, D.C.

- Developed the Django/Python/React/Typescript/MySQL online news website and the Django Admin.
- Generated 300% increase in revenue for the Press Release product by converting a basic HTML form into a more robust and user-friendly single-page React application.
- Developed React/Typescript components and a Django REST Framework API, which enabled features such as bulk purchases, discount codes, and Stripe payments, incorporating both server-side and client-side validation.
- Reduced average debugging time by 50% by enabling breakpoint-debugging of code running inside Docker containers, in both Visual Studio Code and PyCharm.

The Motley Fool

May 2019 - March 2020 (Contract)

Senior Software Engineer (Contract)

Alexandria, VA

- Developed the Django/Python/Postgres reporting dashboard for the online publication's marketing department.
- Increased insight into SEO performance by writing and scheduling custom AWS Lambda functions to scrape Google search results.

Government Executive Media Group - Atlantic Media

September 2017 - May 2019

Senior Software Engineer

Washington, D.C.

- Developed the Django/Python/MySQL online news websites and the Django Admin using Django/Jinja templates, HTML, CSS, and Javascript/jQuery.
- Led the implementation of Agile/Scrum development, including sprints, retroactives, and JIRA tickets/epics.
- Generated \$10,000 in weekly ad sales revenue by implementing an HTML5/CSS video ad on our landing page.
- Upgraded our *Nextgov* and *Government Executive* websites to a modern responsive web design, which were both subsequently nominated for a web design award on Folio.
- Interviewed, hired, and mentored fellow engineers.

U.S. News & World Report

February 2014 - September 2017

Senior Software Engineer / Tech Lead

Washington, D.C.

- Led development of the Content Management System for the Cars, Travel, and Real Estate rankings websites.
- Increased annual revenue by \$400,000 for the Used Cars sales product by developing a custom Python ETL application that processed more than 4 million used car listings from various data partners.
- Developed a Django REST Framework API that delivered cached results to the frontend Used Cars search website.
- Achieved 500% improvement in time efficiency (5 days to 2 hours) for our team of writers by creating an automated scraping framework that retrieved car deals from numerous vehicle manufacturer websites.
- Interviewed and hired senior Django developers.

Deloitte

February 2009 - December 2013

Technology Consultant / Tech Lead

Arlington, VA

- Developed a C#/.NET web application for the U.S. Department of State, which enabled hundreds of government officials to efficiently process a \$6 billion budget through a hierarchical workflow of various agencies.
- Established a robust testing framework by writing over 300 unit tests.
- Lowered annual costs by \$15,000 by reassessing IBM Cognos Reports usage and reducing license purchases.
- Received a letter of commendation from the client for outstanding performance in understanding the business requirements, delivering high-quality and secure application features, and meeting critical government deadlines.
- Interviewed and hired junior developers, and mentored them in both C# and .NET

EDUCATION

University of Michigan - Ann Arbor, MI

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science Engineering

WORK PERMIT

U.S. Citizen